Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subscribe on homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subscribe on homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Your majesty has been working day and night.
Please have some tea to refresh yourself.
The harem is no less complicated than state affairs.
You must have worked as hard as I have.
It is the memorandum from General Nian, isn’t it?
Mm ... He says the wars in the northwest are proceeding well.
While General Nian charges on the battlefield,
his sister prances around in the harem.
The Imperial Kitchen reported that Xiao Tang confessed
his misconduct in storing the ingredients.
He claimed that it was his oversight to
have mixed in the cassava starch
and caused Princess Wenyi's illness.
The Imperial Kitchen is awaiting
Your Majesty's order as to how to deal with him.
They were very efficient in discovering the culprit.
Although they have identified the person,
it's up to Your Majesty whether to end the investigation.
What do you think?
Your Majesty won't be able to focus on state affairs
if the harem is not at peace.
Someone in high power is
repeatedly creating disturbances in the harem.
She has now even used the princess to defame
Your Majesty's beloved concubine.
I believe we should not encourage such behavior.
An unpeaceful harem will disturb the imperial court.
I'm afraid further investigation will
undermine the morale of the soldiers.
So much for the investigation.
(laughing inwardly) If so, Your Majesty must
thoughtfully comfort Lady Sourire.
I understand.
What about Xiao Tang?
Flog to death.
My hands are sweating.
I will go wash my hands in case I stain the embroidery.
Jade.
My Lady, would you like some tea and snacks?
I remember you picked up some
cassava starch to make tapioca pearls.
You can bring some for dessert.
My Lady ... why do you desire it all of a sudden?
I thought they were bad luck so I threw them all away.
What a shame ...
I was thinking about the taste of it.
Lingrong, would you like some chestnut cakes from
His Majesty with a bowl of "eight treasure porridge"?
Anything you would like to have, Sourire.
- Please bring some here.
- Yes.
What did you bring?
I peeled some lianzi [莲子 lotus seeds] for Your Majesty.
It helps to relieve summer heat.
Thank you for doing that. I hope you didn't
hurt your fingernails when peeling them.
Your Majesty usually has dried lotus seeds in soup.
I have removed the cores of the fresh lotus seeds.
They have a special taste.
Mm ... They do taste special.
But the lotus seeds lose flavor without the bitter cores
I thought Your Majesty would not appreciate
the heart of lianzi [怜子sympathy for one's child].
That was why I removed it.
You removed the heart of lianzi [lotus seed] ...
but your heart of lianzi [sympathy] is deep and bitter.
I overheard the eunuchs gossiping this morning ...
about Consort Jing of the Wanli Emperor.
She is given to using her child to gain the emperor's favor.
She once made her child feverish
to garner the Emperor's attention.
What do you think?
If I were the Wanli Emperor, I would
kill Consort Jing to restore discipline in the palace.
Only a mother can understand the pain of
carrying a child from conception to birth.
A mother would never harm her own child ...
unless Consort Jing was not the birth mother.
Even if she had a good reason,
she did not deserve to live
You are usually soft spoken.
It is rare to hear you talk so indignantly.
I apologize for my temper.
It's only that as a mother, I couldn't help
having strong feelings about it.
A father has the same heart of lianzi as the mother.
You put a lot of thought to take out the heart of lianzi.
You are an attentive and patient mother.
After all, Concort Fleur has no experience in caring for a baby.
You should take your child back to your own care.
I thank Your Majesty.
You can take Wenyi home now.
Yes.
Your Majesty, Lady Cao seems to be in a good mood.
But why is Your Majesty looking upset?
What was Lady Cao like when she left?
Lady Cao was almost flying out of the hall.
She headed straight towards the Cooling Hall.
Your Majesty, I misspoke.
My offence deserves punishment.
You spoke the truth.
I saw it as well.
That is exactly why I'm sorely disappointed
Your Majesty, Consort Fleur invites you for some snacks.
Your Majesty hasn't selected a name tag yet.
Recently, Your Majesty has not visited Lady Sourire
and Attendant An, or even Consort Fleur.
You can leave now.
Yes.
Su Peisheng.
Yes, Your Majesty.
I'm feeling a little hungry.
I will ask the Imperial Kitchen to
prepare some snacks for Your Majesty.
Didn't Consort Fleur offer some already?
I understand.
I will follow Your Majesty.
Also, tell Lady Sourire that I will have
breakfast with her in the morning.
Yes.
Hurry up, My Lady is awake.
You go first. I will be there shortly.
His Majesty is coming to have breakfast with My Lady.
I will go now. Don't take too long.
I need to pay my respects to Her Majesty after breakfast.
This hairpin is ostentatious.
My Lady, you are overly cautious.
Although Attendant An is not as favored as you,
she always adorns herself with pretentious jewelry.
Attendant An does not exceed
the norms of her status wearing jewelry.
You'd better not talk like this again.
A prying ear might hear that and think I don't desire her to fare well.
Yes, My Lady.
Attendant An is not very beautiful or well born.
I wonder why His Majesty is so fond of her.
Is it only for her beautiful voice?
His Majesty favors a concubine regardless of her face or family.
All that matters is whether His Majesty likes her.
Otherwise, any effort would be futile.
Lately you've been reckless in your speech.
Prudence was always one of your merits. Remember that.
His Majesty bids you to have breakfast with him, My Lady.
You should wear brighter colors.
Well, you are brightly adorned today.
My Lady, today is the Zhong Yuan Festival [Ghost Festival] .
Bright colors balance the strong yin of the day.
Ah, today is Zhong Yuan Festival.
There will be rituals on the lake tonight.
Paper ships will be burned and
sacrifices will be offered for our ancestors.
You should attend the rituals to accomplish your filial duty. [The festival honors deceased relatives]
Thank you, My Lady.
Vermilion.
Please go check out the food in the kitchen.
I told them the food must be delicious and delicate.
Yes.
Your Majesty has been working very hard.
I have ordered them to make ginseng soup.
It will be ready after court.
Thank you for getting up early with me.
You should go back to sleep.
You can ask them to send the soup to the Governance Hall.
If so ... I will await Your Majesty to have lunch together.
I am very busy today. I will visit you tomorrow.
I thought Your Majesty was angry with me about Princess Wenyi.
I thought you did not want to see me again.
Don't be silly.
Oh, your brother was asking about you
in his memorandum yesterday.
My brother's care for me has not wavered since we were children.
I'm always concerned for him as well.
I wonder if his old injuries got better.
Siblings should always care for each other.
I have replied to him that everything's good with you.
And I also asked about his injuries and
sent some medicine to him on your behalf.
Ah ... I am grateful for Your Majesty's care and consideration.
Your Majesty, since we are performing rituals
for Zhong Yuan Festival,
I have prepared paper offerings for
the soldiers who died on the battlefield.
Let the the priests guide their souls to the Pure Land.
Mm. I appreciate that.
I'm glad that you are so considerate. (laughs)
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
- Rise.
- I thank Your Majesty.
I am hungry after court.
I received some delicious pickles
and had them sent to your kitchen.
Let's have some with the porridge.
Your Majesty, have some soy milk -
we made it this morning.
Your Majesty looks very pleased.
Is there any good news?
Nian Gengyao has won a sweeping victory in the Northwest.
I'm very relieved.
It couldn't have been achieved without Your Majesty's
strategic planning and leadership.
I congratulate Your Majesty with
this bowl of porridge instead of wine.
You think you can escape wine with that?
Your Majesty can't force me to drink.
We will go back to the palace by the end of this month.
It will be a busy time for the empress.
I am afraid she will be exhausted.
I'm considering having Consort Fleur assist her.
What do you think?
What does Her Majesty think?
I haven't talked to her about it.
I came to you first.
There's nothing improper with Your Majesty
trusting Consort Fleur with this task.
I have to say that Consort Fleur makes rash decisions sometimes.
But Consort Honnête is unwell
and Consort Astuce is stodgy and timid.
Consort Fleur is the only one who can help her.
Your Majesty is very considerate.
I believe Her Majesty will not disagree.
The only concern is if Your Majesty restores Consort Fleur's power when General Nian has just won a war,
although we understand that Your Majesty
did it out of care for Her Majesty,
some might misjudge Your Majesty.
They might say that Your Majesty simply
relies on the Nian family to win the wars
and that Your Majesty takes Consort Fleur seriously
only to win over the Nians.
What nonsense in the palace!
Those woodenheads are always fond of gossiping.
Your Majesty must not pay attention to it.
However, General Nian must have been
overjoyed by the feat of victory.
If Your Majesty empowers Consort Fleur right now,
General Nian might be eaten up with pride.
That would not be good.
I was over my head to pass comment on state affairs.
I beg Your Majesty's forgiveness.
It's all right. I have given you permission to talk about governance.
I'm afraid no one else in the palace dares to
discuss the pros and cons like you.
I didn't say it out of jealousy of Her Highness.
I hope Your Majesty will reconsider and
postpone the resumption of Consort Fleur's power.
This will not only quiet down the gossip,
but also maintain the authority of Your Majesty,
and it's more justifiable to confer a title
on Her Highness on a major festival.
Today is Zhongyuan Festival, an ominous day.
Mid-Autumn Festival is approaching,
and New Year follows after.
But New Year is not appropriate for conferrals...
we might have to wait until Lantern Festival
[the end of Spring Festival].
It's not too late to do it next year ...
It's all right, just too much work for the Empress.
Your Majesty need not worry.
Her Majesty is familiar with the palace affairs.
Everything will be all right with the assistance from
Consort Astuce and Concubine Estime.
When Meizhuang was a Noble Lady,
Your Majesty was very appreciative of her.
Your Majesty permitted her to learn about palace management to potentially help Her Majesty with the chores.
It is a pity that now ...
Liu Ben is still at large.
She needs to reflect on her mistake and cultivate virtue.
Yes, justice will be done for Meizhuang once Liu Ben is arrested.
You may rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty must be thirsty after talking for a while.
Would you like some soy milk?
Allow me.
Your Majesty, please.
You are dressed quite smartly today.
I thank your Majesty.
Your green dress is fine and delicate, but it looks
rather gaudy with a pink flower ...
and pink shoes.
I just received a piece of pink satin.
You can make a dress with it.
It will look better than this green dress.
Thank you so much, My Lady.
Allow me to take my leave.
You are very kind to your servants.
Their lives are already tough as servants in the palace.
I must be nice to them to make their life easier.
I agree.
The servants will not fulfill their duty
if they hold any grudge against you.
Your Majesty, the military officials
have been waiting at the Imperial Study.
I have to go now. I will see you tomorrow.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
I didn't expect to see such a beautiful scene of raindrops
falling from pear blossoms [a weeping beauty].
Peace to Noble Prince Guo.
You may rise. Which palace are you from?
I am Lady Sourire's dowry maid.
I thank Your Lordship for your kind words.
However, a pear blossom wearing green with pink is not appreciated.
Who said so?
Somebody just did.
Even if he doesn’t like a flower in green and pink,
the beauty of a flower is different to each beholder.
I think it is quite beautiful.
Your Lordship need not to lie to cheer me up.
Why would I lie? I'm telling the truth.
You can look at the spring flowers if you don't believe me.
Most of them are in pink colors with green leaves.
And everyone thinks they are beautiful.
Your Lordship teases me.
You are beautiful no matter what you wear.
You will be even more extraordinary if you are educated.
You will learn a lot from Lady Sourire.
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subscribe on homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
My Lady, Jade was crying when she ran out.
And she still hasn't come back.
Let her be.
You may go, Vermillion.
I understand why you are upset, My Lady.
A thief living in the house is
much more dangerous than an intruder.
You noticed it as well?
My Lady, pardon my saying that
Jade was acting too obtrusively at the table.
I appreciate your thoughtfulness.
Not everyone is aware of that.
I treat her as my own sister,
but she couldn't wait to stand out.
My Lady, are you still going to reward her the satin?
Of course I will.
Along with the pearl necklace on my dresser.
His Majesty apparently shows no interest in her.
I can't wait to see what she will wear next time!
Yes.
I suspect that Jade has something to do with
the trouble Cao Qinmo gave me at the Governance Hall.
And even the illness of Princess Wenyi.
She was the one who brought back
the cassava starch, wasn't she?
Yes ... (sigh) it's hard to see into a person.
I'm wondering whether she's sided with Consort Fleur or Lady Cao.
In my view, Consort Fleur wouldn't deal with her directly.
It must be Lady Cao.
This girl ... born low but aims high.
She wasted all my consideration for her future.
Act as if nothing happened when you give her the rewards
in case she does something out of guilt.
I understand, My Lady.
That bitch dares to impede me!
Your Highness need not be angry.
His Majesty intends to reinstate your
authority to assist in palace affairs, it's just a matter of time.
Lady Sourire could stop Your Highness once,
but will she be able to interfere again?
I wonder if His Majesty has suspicions about Wenyi's illness.
That's why His Majesty would listen to that bitch Zhen Huan.
Your Highness must not worry.
General Nian has just won a succession of battles.
Nothing else could make His Majesty happier.
Why would His Majesty be suspicious?
His Majesty has been visiting me frequently.
Was that because of my brother?
Your Highness is overthinking.
Nothing is more common than seeing His Majesty in our palace.
This is evidence enough to see that
His Majesty has always trusted Your Highness.
That's true.
I don't mind if His Majesty does not resume my authority.
If His Majesty does, it will look like it is
because of my brother rather than me.
His Majesty postponed because he cares for me.
His Majesty empowers me because I'm his wife,
not because of an external relative.
Exactly, Your Highness should feel completely at ease.
Cao
It’s so rare to have you over, Sourire!
I heard that Princess Wenyi is back.
I missed her very much so I dropped by.
I hope I'm welcomed here.
You must be joking, Sourire.
I have always hoped to have you over.
I'm just afraid that you would still be mad
about the foolish mistake I made.
I am worried that you would still be holding on to that.
That's why I am here.
We serve His Majesty as a family.
No miscommunication should stand between us sisters.
Exactly.
Although I am few years older than you,
I'm not as wise as you are.
I listened to some idiots and caused you so much trouble.
I deserve punishment.
Let bygones be bygones.
I apologize for barging in.
I hope you don't mind me, Cao.
Not at all.
Vermillion.
Yes, My Lady.
I embroidered these bodices myself for Princess Wenyi.
They are a small token of my regard.
I hope you don't mind my unremarkable needlework.
Here is some rouge that Jinxi made in her free time.
It creates a fine and glowing complexion.
You might want to give it a try.
How thoughtful you are, Sourire!
This is so beautifully done!
Here, look at this flower ...
I could almost smell the sweet scent of it.
These are all commonplace items.
I have yet another gift for you, Cao ...
but I'm afraid it's not very appropriate here.
May I speak to you in the inner chamber?
Certainly, this way please, Sourire.
You must accept this, Cao.
Sourire, why are you doing this?
This is too precious a gift.
I must not accept it.
Please take it back, Sourire.
I was hoping to ask you a favor.
I'm embarrassed to say it if you decline my gift.
You can tell me straight out, Sourire.
I will not decline if there's anything I can help you with.
Her Highness Consort Fleur is distinguished and graceful.
She commands my greatest admiration.
But somehow, unintentionally, I have incurred
offense and misunderstanding from Her Highness.
I'm pitifully alone in the palace,
and even more isolated since Companion Shen's confinement.
Cao, I beg you would have pity on me.
Sourire, you are deeply favored by His Majesty
and Attendant An is like a sister to you.
Why would you feel that way?
His Majesty would still visit me for my freshness in the palace.
Now that An is in favor, I dread to think about my status in the future.
(sigh) Your words evoke sadness in me.
But I'm in no better position.
Although I have Wenyi, she is a princess after all.
Her Highness Consort Fleur trusts you.
I humbly hope you can put in a good word for me.
I would be infinitely grateful
if Her Highness would bestow grace on me.
Her Highness will understand your feelings in time.
However, ...
this is too valuable, you should take it back.
I will do my best to talk to Her Highness.
If so, I will render my humble service to Her Highness and you.
The Emerald Honey was a gift from His Majesty.
It is an exotic tributary perfume.
They only offered a small box of it.
I hope you like it.
It's the Emerald Honey.
It gives a pleasantly subtle scent.
That is an extraordinary perfume.
My cuff was scented by just opening the box.
My Lady, when you had just left,
Lady Cao's palace discarded your gifts secretly.
Why would she genuinely accept my gift?
Was the perfume discarded too?
Huh? What perfume? I didn't see any.
That's all I need to know. You can go now.
My Lady, how were you so sure
that Lady Cao would accept the Emerald Honey?
She always has to know her place under Consort Fleur,
maintaining a lifestyle strictly appropriate to her rank.
Looking at her plain chamber, you would know
that she must have never had such a luxury.
And the Emerald Honey is rare indeed.
No woman would resist it unless
they dislike perfumes like Her Majesty.
Although she was on her guard,
she couldn't bear to throw it away.
Great prospect belongs to people who can reject opulence.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
With the books "perfumed by a red cuff",
I won't feel the tediousness of work any more.
Your Majesty allowed me to visit the Imperial Study.
I must bring in peace of mind.
Jade, I'm going to the Leisured Moon Chamber to meet Meizhuang.
My Lady, why did you decide to go all of a sudden?
His Majesty has ordered that no one shall visit her without permission.
I have been thinking about her constantly.
I have to ask her about something face to face.
Jade, you are my dowry maid.
Very few people have seen you in the palace.
I will pretend to be you and deliver some packages to her with Jinxi.
I have taken care of the people over there.
I will sneak in as the night falls,
when the guards change shifts.
It will be perfectly safe.
But My Lady, you would be guilty of deceiving His Majesty were you caught.
You are in high favor now and need not take such a risk.
I will just need to walk with my head down.
No one will notice.
I have to make this trip whether in high favor or not.
His Majesty will sleep alone tonight.
I cannot miss this chance.
My Lady, please think twice before you go.
I know what I'm doing.
Jade, you will stay in the chamber.
Don't let anyone else see you.
Okay.
Let's go.
-Madam, are you going out?
-Mm
My Lady, please go inside and get changed.
Xiao-Yunzi has been waiting for you.
I hope I'm wrong about this.
You can go now.
Be vigilant.
Yes.
My Lady.
-Is Her Highness here?
-Yes.
Xiao-Yunzi, you will wait here.
Yes.
Peace and grace to Your Highness.
Aiya, you came without a sound.
That surprised me.
Your Highness seems to be in a good mood.
I was just bored, so I was making this bodice.
Come here.
Have a look at my bodice.
Ruyi, bring some tea.
Yes.
It's okay.
I'd just like to talk with Your Highness.
They will interrupt our conversation.
That's right.
I also find their presence inhibiting sometimes.
It's not like they are under my control,
but quite the other way around.
Your Highness finds peace in solitude.
It is never peaceful enough in the palace.
How can we live our lives if we can't find peace in ourselves?
I appreciate Your Highness's advice.
Her Highness Consort Fleur.
Consort Fleur?
What brings her here?
She must have her reasons to be here.
Your Highness, Consort Fleur
went to the Leisured Moon Chamber.
She said that Madam Cui passed some packages
into the chamber for Shen.
I see.
Let's wait and see.
Good.
Jinxi only brought some daily necessities and food
and asked me to give them to Companion Shen.
She came with two other maids to help her carry the packages.
But I did not see Lady Sourire.
Like Madam Orchid said, Your Highness, I was simply
delivering the packages at My Lady's request.
I did not disobey His Majesty's order
which forbids anyone to meet with Shen.
Is that so?
She said that you came with two other maids.
Why is there only one standing beside you?
Where is the other maid?
Er...
The other maid is Violet.
She also works for the Palace of Pearl Jade.
I sent her back earlier to do some chores.
Did you?
In that case, I shall not waste my breath arguing with you.
It was reported that someone sneaked into the chamber
without permission to visit a confined concubine.
This violates His Majesty's edict.
I am here to investigate.
I am attending to Shen's confinement at His Majesty's behest.
How could anyone possibly come to meet My Lady?
You never know.
Some concubines are conceited over their status.
They might be as bold as brass.
Your Majesty, Concubine Estime's maid Ruyi is here.
She said that Consort Fleur is creating a disturbance
outside the Leisured Moon Chamber.
Consort Fleur suspects that someone has
snuck into the chamber to meet Shen without permission.
Her Highness is trying to enter the chamber and investigate.
Well, we can't go a day without disturbance.
It seems that Your Majesty is about to get busy again.
Allow me to take my leave.
What an easy life without wives.
I'm so jealous of you.
(laughs) Well, I thought you were troubled
by the composition of the game.
I'll definitely resolve it tonight.
You must not leave.
I don't know when you will be able to come back.
How about we continue the game tomorrow?
If so, you shall not leave the palace tonight.
I'll play with you after court tomorrow.
- Su Peisheng.
- Yes, Your Majesty.
Clean up a room for Noble Prince Guo.
He will stay here tonight.
Yes.
Will Your Lordship mind staying at
the Penglai Island on the lake?
It is a quiet and elegant place
away from the residences of the concubines.
Sounds good.
I will see with my own eyes whether there is an intruder.
Your highness, no one else is inside.
Your Highness need not enter.
According to His Majesty's edict,
I dare not let Your Highness in.
I beg Your Highness's pardon.
How dare you stand in my way?
Your Highness, I dare not.
Out of my way!
Your Highness, I cannot let you in.
His Majesty the Emperor!
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subscribe on homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.